[Music]
welcome back to the real news network
this is reality asserts itself and i'm
paul jay
we're continuing our series of
interviews with john kiriakou who joins
us again in the studio thanks for
joining us
thanks for having me so one more time
john's a former cia
analyst and then became a case officer
and he's author of the book the
reluctant spy my secret life
in the cia's war on terror he spent
about 23 months in jail and is now under
house arrest for
another 40 odd days for being the only
person convicted
to having anything to do with the
torture program in the united states
and no he wasn't convicted for torturing
anybody he was convicted for
whistleblowing
when john joined the cia in 1990 he was
25 years old
how do you get recruited by the cia
in grad school i took a class called
leadership very simply it was taught by
an eminent psychiatrist by the name of
dr gerald post
dr post is one of the country's leading
thinkers
in the area of terrorist
psychology so in this class one of our
assignments was to
shadow our bosses and write a
psychological profile of that boss
at the time i was working at the united
food and commercial workers
international union
in washington long history of labor
involvement in my family
and i wrote a paper and i
said that i believed my boss was a
sociopath
and that he was potentially dangerous
and i offered evidence
to show why i thought he was potentially
dangerous
so i got an a on this paper and in the
margin dr post wrote
i've never done this before but i urge
you to resign from this job
i too believe that your boss is a
sociopath
so i quit and got another job
in the meantime he asked me to stay
after class one day
and he said do you have any uh
job lined up after graduation and i said
uh dr post
not only do i not have a job i don't
even have any prospects for a job
and i'm getting married a couple of
weeks after graduation
so he said have you ever given any
thought to the cia
and i said no not really
you think you'd be interested i said
sure i have nothing else going on and so
he uh took me back to his office
went through his rolodex in the days
when everybody had a rolodex
and as he was going through the rolodex
i remember seeing um
one card that said ollie north home and
it had a number and i thought
who is this guy that he has oliver
north's
home phone number and his rolodex and
this is pretty much in the
in the midst of iran contra or just
after the end of iran contra
so he he calls a number
and says uh bob are you free i have a
good one
and uh hung up the phone and said
you need to go to roslyn uh the rosalind
metro station in arlington virginia
go to this address and ask for bob
so i got on the subway took it one stop
uh to roslyn and i went to this
completely nondescript
building that no longer exists and
went up to the sixth floor and i buzzed
a buzzer
and a uniformed cop of some sort
came out and said are you here for bob i
said i am
so he lets me into a little atrium and
there's another door that has a big
spin lock on it and a cipher like a bank
vault
so he buzzes that door
and it opens and a woman pops her head
out just her head
and she says are you here for bob i said
i'm here for bob
so she lets me in and a minute later
this
huge six foot five 350 pound
guy comes out and with his hand out says
hi
i'm bob are you john i said i am come on
in here john
i talked to him for a few minutes and he
said what i want you to do
is saturday morning at eight o'clock be
at the george washington university
medical center auditorium you're going
to take some tests
i said okay so that saturday morning
i went into town and went to the uh
the medical school auditorium there were
200 people there at least
and the proctors handed out these stacks
of papers
so one was a big map of the world but it
was just blank
all the countries were divided but it
was blank and you had to write in the
name of every country
and i say in my book i was always a map
nut so i just
scribbled in the names of all the
countries and uh
and the next one was a current events
test multiple choice
crazy easy like you didn't even have to
subscribe to a newspaper at the time
if you had just walked by the box
holding the washington post and looked
at the top half of the front page
you could have done well on this test it
was very easy
i finished that quickly and then the
third test was very long
several thousand questions the questions
were all
yes or no and i also mentioned this in
the book
as an example one of the questions was i
like boxing
and the truth is i didn't really care
one way or the other about boxing
mike tyson was prominent at the time and
i liked mike tyson
so i thought well i don't really care
about boxing but if mike tyson's
fighting i'll usually stop and watch it
so i put yes but then like 234 questions
later
it says i like boxing and i thought
geez what did i say the first time i
can't remember i think i said yes
i think i put yes
and then another 400 questions later it
says i like boxing
and i was like geez oh man so you see
what they're doing they're looking for
patterns
so i did it i finished it i finished it
first
of anybody and i sat there for a while
and looked around and nobody else is
getting up so i thought ah
i'm done so i got up i handed it to the
proctor and i walked out
my wife picks me up and she says how'd
you do i said i have no idea
i have no idea how i did i said the
questions were so weird i'm not sure
what they were looking for
a week or so later i get a call from bob
he says you blew the doors off that
that test i want you to go to another
equally nondescript building in vienna
virginia take some more tests were
any of the questions on the test
political what do you think of this we
don't think of that nothing like that
it's all attitudinal
all attitudinal uh the the current
events test was
was so simple it was i i remember one of
the questions was
the prime minister of greece is a
andreas papandreou
b mao zetang
or d youth ant so come on you know
i just blew right through it okay when
you're thinking about joining the cia
first of all it doesn't sound like you
thought too much about it i didn't think
at all about it
but did it not occur to you to think
about the church committee for example
that
that you must have been aware you're a
savvy guy oh yeah this
the church committee just for people
that don't know i mean the church
committee that
investigated terrible misdeeds
assassination attempts
something terrible terrible things the
church committee
revealed and afterwards there were
many investigative pieces in newspapers
and magazines and the cia had done
bad stuff bad stuff that didn't ring for
you
do i want to be part of this i knew i
knew a guy in college whose father
worked at the cia
and i asked him if he would have coffee
with me one day and i asked him
questions
and then there was a uh
woman i knew in grad school whose
boyfriend worked at the cia and i did
the same thing with him we had dinner
one night
and they told me that yes the church
committee had revealed
terrible crimes but by god the cia had
cleaned up its act
and it's a great place to work and
you're going to love it because
everything is good and everything is
clean now and everything's by the book
and i said great that sounds like a
place for me
and who can say no to bob that's right
who could say no to bob
all right so you go to another
nondescript building
and another another bob no i met there
by
three three individuals
a psychologist a psychiatrist and an
anthropologist
and they interview me and they're asking
me questions
like describe your relationship with
your mother
and i said well i have a terrific mother
you know she's always been
supportive we've always gotten along and
they look at each other and
not uh describe your relationship with
your father
or was your father the disciplinarian in
the family
and then finally they asked me a
question that that still sticks with me
have you ever betrayed a friendship and
i said
oh my god i hope not i don't think so
i said let me think about it they said
no no that's the answer we were looking
for
i said okay when that was done they took
hair blood urine sent me on my way
and then a week later bob calls and said
you
aced those tests so we're going to send
for um interviews so he set up a
day's worth of interviews at cia
headquarters
and a couple of weeks after that i got
an offer
in the mail now you wrote in your book i
i believe
that that they like to look for people
with did you call
trending towards social path well a cia
psychiatrist told me one time
that the cia looks to hire people with
sociopathic
tendencies not sociopaths because
sociopaths have no consciences
but people with sociopathic tendencies
are comfortable
operating in moral and legal gray areas
so do you think they found that in you
i think they probably did because at
that time
when they asked me the question they
they offered a a scenario
they said you know
that mr x has something in his house
that you need
whether it's a file or whatever you need
it
and you work on him to recruit him so
that eventually he turns that file over
to you
but he's not recruitable and in the end
when you ask him for the file he tells
you no what do you do
i said i break into the house and take
the file
seemed like a perfectly logical answer
to me because they were
but you understood they were asking oh
of course think like a cia
absolutely i mean did you you believe
that or you were feeding them something
you thought they wanted to hear
no i believed that if if mr x was a
russian scientist let's say
i would absolutely break into his house
and take it
right we're the good guys they're the
bad guys so
sure i believed it so you're hired you
go through orientation and you're
writing the book
that one of the people that's giving you
the orientation i'm quoting
the director of the office of security
made the biggest impression on you
saying something has stayed something
has stayed with you all these years
that he said the greatest threat facing
america today
is the threat of soviet communism and
you didn't take you didn't think so
i thought that was absurd this is
january of 1990
right the berlin wall is down the soviet
union is breaking up
and eastern europe is turning democratic
and
this old man is standing there telling
us that the greatest threat we face is
soviet communism
i thought it was ridiculous and i
wondered if it was just for show
if it was to make us feel like wow we're
really part of something now
but as the years passed i think i've
come to the conclusion that
that he believed it that he was one of
those old-timers who just couldn't
change with the times
just the culture was too embedded what
did you think was the greatest threat
and and were you joining because you
thought there was a threat or you were
joining us of something interesting to
do no i thought it would be interesting
and frankly i was looking forward to the
travel that's really what uh
what was most exciting for me you know i
i really didn't think there was
any any large transnational threat at
the time
except maybe terrorism uh
and i had my own thoughts on on
terrorism
i i believe that the real threat was
nationalist terrorism or communist
terrorism
whether it was the pflp dflp pfl pgc
some of the greek groups the red
brigades the action direct
you know those were the groups that were
killing americans overseas hezbollah
although that was religious and not uh
not nationalist that's where i thought
the real threats were coming
not the former soviet union and that's
what it was at that point it was already
the former soviet union right
so you get in and very quickly you're
sent to
kuwait well i was given
i was given kuwait as a what they called
a
training account i was told you know
kuwait has this very interesting
democratic movement people demonstrate
every once in a while
they're experimenting with a
democratically elected parliament
so learn kuwait learn how to write in
the cia's analytics style and then you
can move on to something really
interesting like romania
that's what the guy told me so i thought
dog got it
i'm going to be stuck with this country
where nothing ever happens i'm never
going to get promoted
this is still you're still in arlington
or you're actually in kuwait no i'm in
arlington still
so i did kuwait for four months and then
in april of 1990 i also picked up iraq
and at the time in the cia
you could count on two hands the number
of people that covered iraq
and i mean in everything analysis
operations everything
press you name it again i was told
that iraq is a good training company
nothing ever changes there
it's the same cabinet since 1968
right no changes nothing happens
no trouble no problems i said okay
now just to be clear for everybody
you're in the analysis section
not the operation section no we had very
poor relations with iraq at the time so
our embassy was
very very small it was something like
four or five people
there wasn't really much reporting
coming out of it i'd read the iraqi
papers every day
or translations of the iraqi papers that
weren't in english
and i was really more focused on on iraq
and then on august 2nd 1990 iraq invaded
kuwait
i should say it was more focused on
kuwait so iraq invaded kuwait
the night before the invasion we
predicted
that the iraqis would of course cross
the border
and i had a softball game that night the
cia has its own softball league
that way if you say something classified
it's okay because everybody's
a cia employee right so i had a softball
game that night
and one of the older guys came up to me
and said
i don't think how i don't think you
understand how important
this iraq kuwait thing is he said it's
one thing for our countries to go to war
with each other the countries that we
cover
it's an entirely different thing for the
country we covered to go to war with us
he said you have a chance here to really
become somebody
so pay close attention and do your
analysis
and how much pressure was there on you
next iraq war style to shape and modify
your analysis
in favor of saddam's totally the bad guy
our hands are clean yeah you mean in
no no no i'm talking back like this when
you're analyzing like for example
yeah prior to the first gulf war it
later came out
how much there was like this
infant that was supposedly
infants being tortured story was
apparently a fraud there's a
pretty good documentation the american
ambassador
uh to iraq let saddam no no
that's not true but i was there that
night she got a bum rap on that that was
ambassador april glaspie right
april glaspie was instructed by the
secretary of state
who was james baker at the time to
go to see saddam and to tell saddam that
the united states will not take a
position
on arab arab border disputes that's all
she said
i don't think ever any more than that's
ever been said
right that she said the interpretation's
been well
that we will not interfere after the
fact the press said that saddam's
interpretation was that that was a green
light but her instructions were not to
give him the green light
i understand i i i as i've always heard
the story
what you said is what she said yeah but
there was
never a suggestion that we would
intervene quite the opposite this is
your business
between you and kuwait and we're going
to stay out of it that was nobody nobody
expected him
to take the entire country frankly we
expected that iraqi troops would move
across the border
and that they would take that narrow
strip on the kuwaiti side that included
the southern tip of the ramella oil
field
that's what everybody expected to happen
because frankly the truth of the matter
is the kuwaitis were drilling
horizontally
so they were drilling in their little
tip of the ramayla oil field
underneath the iraqi border and they
were stealing the oil iraq
stealing iraqi oil stealing iraqi oil
and so
and you knew that at the time everybody
did and it was in the papers and
everything so
everybody including including us
believed that
the iraqis would move across the border
take the oil field and that would be the
end of it
in fact within 24 hours they took the
entire country and then just began
murdering everybody the uh
but some of the murder stories were
exaggerated this murder of infants
yeah i never understood why the kuwaitis
felt compelled to exaggerate those
stories because there were so many
despicable crimes against humanity that
iraqi soldiers were committing
in kuwait there was no reason to lie
about them i remember when
when the girl that you're speaking about
testified before
congress i remember watching that at the
c.i.a
and saying i know that girl isn't she
just
the kuwaiti ambassador's daughter that's
so nassar's daughter
so i mean it only took but a day or two
to break the story that
this whole thing was a setup right and
frankly
the kuwaitis the kuwaitis were guilty of
of um
of of lying and trying to propagandize
the situation
but so was their public relations firm i
don't think the quadies came up with
that on their own
and when you say everyone expected to
come in and just take the oil field
then it's not that much of a stretch for
saddam said well i have a green light to
take the oil field
at the time i would have said that that
was insane
i can see how he may have believed that
he had a green light
but ambassador glasby certainly did not
believe she was giving him a green light
because the overall suggestion is
that u.s policymakers wanted saddam to
go
give him some rope to hang himself
because they want an excuse to
to have the first war i never believed
that because saddam was the only thing
that we had standing between iran and
the small gulf countries
we needed saddam and the iranians to
just
kill each other for decades well that's
the same argument about the next
saddam war except they didn't stop the
invasion right
so one can wonder yeah well that just
goes to show you what a stupid policy we
had in 2003
to to provoke this war with the iraqis
because now
we've created a regional hegemon in uh
in iran
we took out an entire an entire
sect of iraq and and we've we've
disenfranchised sunnis
we've taken their positions we've taken
them out of government and out of the
military
and you have an entirely shia military
in iraq now
that is that is in some ways supportive
of uh of iran's theocracy
and in other ways uh accepting of it
we're gonna carry on with your story uh
from kuwait further in the next segment
of our interview
please join us for the continuation of
reality asserts itself with john
kiriakou
on the real news network
[Music]
you